<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>En on Blog: Romain Berthon</title>
    <link>https://romaintrm.github.io/tags/en/</link>
    <description>Recent content in En on Blog: Romain Berthon</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 09:00:24 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://romaintrm.github.io/tags/en/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>REFINING SOFTWARE ARCHITECTURES</title>
      <link>https://romaintrm.github.io/posts/refining-software-architectures/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 09:00:24 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://romaintrm.github.io/posts/refining-software-architectures/</guid>
      <description>To develop software, as developers we have to choose between several architectures. Our choice must be based on various constraints like the type of problem we&amp;rsquo;re trying to solve, but also the load or the level of reliability and resiliency targeted. We also have to consider the available skills in the team.&#xA;In this blog post, I want to iterate through several back-end architectures I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered and used during my career.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>THE &#34;TECHNOLOGICAL ADULTHOOD&#34;</title>
      <link>https://romaintrm.github.io/posts/the-technological-adulthood/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://romaintrm.github.io/posts/the-technological-adulthood/</guid>
      <description>Few months ago, I&amp;rsquo;ve read this article: How We Built a Self-Healing System to Survive a Terrifying Concurrency Bug At Netflix.&#xA;What I loved is how unconventional the solution was. However, unconventional doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean irrelevant, their solution kept the software running during the weekend, and this without any human intervention. The solution wasn&amp;rsquo;t perfect, but it was &amp;ldquo;good enough&amp;rdquo; and even more, respectful of people&amp;rsquo;s time.&#xA;By the end, it concludes with a concept that somehow inspired me: &amp;ldquo;technological adulthood&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>APPLYING THE &#39;/AI MANIFESTO&#39;</title>
      <link>https://romaintrm.github.io/posts/applying-the-ai-manifesto/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://romaintrm.github.io/posts/applying-the-ai-manifesto/</guid>
      <description>Recently, Antoine Caron published a blog post about his AI usage. Thanks to him, I&amp;rsquo;ve discovered the /ai &amp;lsquo;manifesto&amp;rsquo; and I want to do the same here. Maybe you&amp;rsquo;ve reached this post by typing /ai in the URL.&#xA;MY POSTS All the posts in this blog are written by myself, I don&amp;rsquo;t use any generative AI to produce content.&#xA;Creating a blog post is an interesting activity, it requires me to challenge and organize my thoughts before trying to write on a topic.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>USING PROCESSES FOR BETTER RESILIENCE</title>
      <link>https://romaintrm.github.io/posts/using-processes-for-better-resilience/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://romaintrm.github.io/posts/using-processes-for-better-resilience/</guid>
      <description>In early 2020, I&amp;rsquo;ve read the book Programming Elixir 1.6. At that time I had one goal: to have an introduction to the actor model with a language that supports it by design, in this case Elixir. I think it was a good read and I achieved my goal, even though I didn&amp;rsquo;t feel able to design a complete system using this pattern.&#xA;However, I realized I&amp;rsquo;m using some actor model concepts for a few years now.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CQRS/ES: HOW TO ACHIEVE A GOOD EVENT GRANULARITY?</title>
      <link>https://romaintrm.github.io/posts/cqrs-es-how-to-achieve-a-good-event-granularity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://romaintrm.github.io/posts/cqrs-es-how-to-achieve-a-good-event-granularity/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;ve already developed a software using the event sourcing pattern, you&amp;rsquo;ve probably faced difficulty: How-to design good events? What is a good event granularity?&#xA;Indeed it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to produce good events that will not harm our design. As a seasoned developer with event sourcing, I&amp;rsquo;m still struggling with this, even if I&amp;rsquo;ve developed several heuristics over time.&#xA;In this blog post, I will share with you these heuristics. But keep in mind this is not some kind of best practices.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ZERO DOWNTIME DATABASE MIGRATION</title>
      <link>https://romaintrm.github.io/posts/zero-downtime-database-migration/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 09:13:43 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://romaintrm.github.io/posts/zero-downtime-database-migration/</guid>
      <description>Nowadays, most of the services we&amp;rsquo;re using are online and available 24/7. If, like me, you&amp;rsquo;re working on a company that provide this kind of service, you&amp;rsquo;re probably aiming for such availability. As I&amp;rsquo;ve already highlighted it, it has a huge influence on how you should code and deploy your software. Indeed, to maximize availability, you&amp;rsquo;re probably aiming for a zero downtime deployment.&#xA;Zero downtime deployment includes several topics. Today I want to focus on how to achieve a database migration without service interruption.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>STATE-BASED AND EVENT-BASED APPROACHES</title>
      <link>https://romaintrm.github.io/posts/state-based-and-event-based-approaches/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 13:02:48 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://romaintrm.github.io/posts/state-based-and-event-based-approaches/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve recently gave a talk with my friend Aurélien about the heuristics we&amp;rsquo;ve developed after using CQRS/ES for several years.&#xA;After our talk, we had a chat with some developers. We concluded that choosing a state-based oriented approach (like CRUD) seems to be the default solution, such choice seems to remain unchallenged. On the opposite side, choosing an event-based systems (event sourced or event driven) will very often be heavily challenged.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AN ENJOYABLE MISSION: RETURN OF EXPERIENCE</title>
      <link>https://romaintrm.github.io/posts/an-enjoyable-mission-return-of-experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 20:53:08 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://romaintrm.github.io/posts/an-enjoyable-mission-return-of-experience/</guid>
      <description>I had the chance to work few months in Agicap, an enterprise producing a cashflow management SAAS for businesses.&#xA;It was a great mission, my team worked a way that I consider to be, so far, the most efficient and pleasant in my career. We managed to produce value at a constant speed while keeping a full control of our code, not allowing any kind of quality depreciation over time.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
